<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-07-05T20:18:50+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/</id><title type="html">LendFirst Home Loans</title><subtitle>LendFirst offers smart advice and real solutions for first home buyers and first-time investors, in Cairns, Queeensland, Australia.</subtitle><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><entry><title type="html">How many Avocado Smashes would $20,000 buy?</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/how-many-avocado-smashes-would-20000-buy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How many Avocado Smashes would $20,000 buy?" /><published>2017-07-05T19:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-07-05T19:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/how-many-avocado-smashes-would-$20000-buy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/how-many-avocado-smashes-would-20000-buy/">&lt;p&gt;For those that missed the punchline, an Australian millionaire recently suggested millennials stop buying an Avocado Smash to save for a house deposit and his comments went viral around the globe (read the article &lt;a href=&quot;www.news.com.au/finance/money/costs/avocado-toast-mortgages-have-gone-global/news-story/0e691bfafc89e2d1511a7cbdfd074e9c&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Now that the Queensland First Home Buyers Grant of $20,000 has been extended until 31st December 2017, I wondered how long it would take to save $20,000 if I stopped buying avocado on toast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, 9 years… Assuming I paid $22 for an Avocado smash and I had one twice a week, every week of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There could be an easier way if you are a First Home Buyer. Some lenders may let you ‘pretend’ the $20,000 grant is your own savings so if your ‘real’ savings is small, buying or building your First Home today might just be possible. The lending criteria is very complex and you should speak to a mortgage broker who specialises in First Home Buyers as the wrong advice could mean the difference between owning your own home or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the main requirements to qualify for the government $20k grant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must be buying or building a ‘Brand New’ home under $750,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You or your spouse must not have previously owned property in Australia before&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must live in the house as your primary residence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must be 18yrs old&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must be an Australian Citizen or Permanent Resident (or applying with someone who is)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://firsthomeowners.initiatives.qld.gov.au/&quot;&gt;Queensland First Home Owners Grant&lt;/a&gt; or contact the Qld Office of State Revenue directly on 1300 300 734 to find out if you are eligible before considering or discussing your finance options.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">For those that missed the punchline, an Australian millionaire recently suggested millennials stop buying an Avocado Smash to save for a house deposit and his comments went viral around the globe (read the article here). Now that the Queensland First Home Buyers Grant of $20,000 has been extended until 31st December 2017, I wondered how long it would take to save $20,000 if I stopped buying avocado on toast.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-how-many-avocado-smashes-would-$20000-buy.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Important Contract Clauses—Cooling Off Period</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/important-contract-clauses-cooling-off-period/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Important Contract Clauses—Cooling Off Period" /><published>2017-06-27T20:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-27T20:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/important-contract-clauses-cooling-off-period</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/important-contract-clauses-cooling-off-period/">&lt;p&gt;The Cooling Off Period is the period after a buyer enters a contract to buy home or land in which the buyer can terminate the contract without having to provide a reason or justification to the seller. Notification must be provided in writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-long-does-it-last-for&quot;&gt;How long does it last for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 business days&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-day-does-it-start&quot;&gt;What day does it start?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day the buyer receives a signed contract executed by all parties.  If this day is a weekend, the cooling off period starts from the next business day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-does-it-end&quot;&gt;When does it end?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 5pm on the 5th day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;are-there-costs&quot;&gt;Are there costs?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seller has the right to charge the buyer a penalty of 0.25% of the purchase price.  If a larger deposit has been paid, then the balance of the deposit must be returned to the buyer within 14days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-the-buyer-waive-the-cooling-off-period&quot;&gt;Can the buyer waive the cooling off period?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes but it must be provided in writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-the-seller-waive-the-cooling-off-period&quot;&gt;Can the seller waive the cooling off period?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-exempt-from-a-cooling-off-clause&quot;&gt;What is exempt from a cooling off clause?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A contract where the property is purchased at auction or is purchased before 5pm the day after the auction and the buyer was a registered bidder.  Some other exclusions apply however these should be discussed with your legal representative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above information is general in nature and does not constitute legal advice.  This information has been summarised from and can be viewed in full at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.qld.gov.au/law/laws-regulated-industries-and-accountability/queensland-laws-and-regulations/regulated-industries-and-licensing/regulated-industries-licensing-and-legislation/property-industry-regulation/legal-requirements-for-the-property-industry/cooling-off-period-for-residential-property-contracts/&quot;&gt;the Queensland Government website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is strongly recommended buyers and sellers seek legal advice to answer any questions about their individual circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">The Cooling Off Period is the period after a buyer enters a contract to buy home or land in which the buyer can terminate the contract without having to provide a reason or justification to the seller. Notification must be provided in writing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Family BBQs are the First Home Buyer’s worst enemy</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/family-bbqs-are-the-first-home-buyers-worst-enemy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Family BBQs are the First Home Buyer's worst enemy" /><published>2017-06-20T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-20T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/family-bbqs-are-the%20first-home-buyers-worst-enemy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/family-bbqs-are-the-first-home-buyers-worst-enemy/">&lt;p&gt;What would happen if we re-plumbed the house on advice from a doctor or if we committed to surgery on the advice of a driving instructor and what would happen if we learnt how to drive on the advice from a plumber?  Sounds crazy I know but we do this all the time and we don’t realise it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone understands that to put in a new toilet, we speak to a plumber or to have surgery we chat to a doctor and the best person to teach us how to drive is a driving instructor but why do we continually follow the advice of parents, brothers, sisters and friends when it comes to home loan advice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge for a mortgage broker, is explaining to borrowers, particularly first home buyers why a specific bank, product or loan feature worked for their parents but won’t for them.  It usually stems from a conversation ending with the words “this worked really well for us, you should do it to!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it did work well but not everyone has the same income, deposit or credit history and just because it worked well for someone else, doesn’t mean it will for you.
Unless your parents, family &amp;amp; friends are mortgage brokers, acknowledge their opinion but please, do yourself a favour and follow advice from the people most qualified to give it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">What would happen if we re-plumbed the house on advice from a doctor or if we committed to surgery on the advice of a driving instructor and what would happen if we learnt how to drive on the advice from a plumber? Sounds crazy I know but we do this all the time and we don’t realise it!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Comparison rates</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/comparison-rates/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Comparison rates" /><published>2017-06-13T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-13T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/comparison-rates</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/comparison-rates/">&lt;p&gt;A comparison rate is a tool to help consumers identify the true cost of a loan by reducing the costs of a loan—including interest &amp;amp; fees—into a single percentage rate to easily compare the true cost of home loans.  We can use comparison rates to compare various loans from different lenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-we-have-them&quot;&gt;Why do we have them?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reveal any hidden costs or charges associated with a home loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-are-they-calculated&quot;&gt;How are they calculated?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application Fees and ongoing fees are reduced to a single percentage rate and added to the actual rate for comparison. If a loan has no fees the comparison rate should be the same as the actual rate. Here’s an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lender A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lender B&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amount&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Term&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30yrs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30yrs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Actual Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.24%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.39%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Application Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$600&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$600&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$395 per year&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Comparison Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.42%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.41%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-lender-b-is-the-better-option-then&quot;&gt;So Lender B is the better option then?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not necessarily.  Advertised comparison rates don’t include fee waivers, discounts or other benefits. In the example, Lender A regularly waives the application fee on request but Lender B does not.  This would make Lender A’s comparison rate 4.40%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-else-should-i-be-cautious-about-comparison-rates&quot;&gt;Why else should I be cautious about comparison rates?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The calculation does not take into account financial benefits gained from other features associated with the home loan such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest savings from a 100% offset account or loan trimmer account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Associated fee waivers on credit cards or bank accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Associated discounts on insurances and other services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-is-a-comparison-rate-good-for-then&quot;&gt;So what is a comparison rate good for then?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are very good when comparing introductory/fixed rate loans as the comparison is based on the full loan term not just the intro period.  Here’s an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lender A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lender B&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amount&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Term&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30yrs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30yrs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3yr Intro Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.99%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.99%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;After 3yr Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5.24%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.24%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Application Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$600&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$600&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$10 mth&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$10 mth&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Comparison Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.97%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.22%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The large difference in comparison rates quickly raises an alarm. It has revealed Lender A’s catch to their special offer.  That is a much higher rate after the intro term.  The comparison rate very quickly identified this issue without the borrower having to do too much analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;should-i-rely-on-comparison-rates-to-decide-what-loan-is-best&quot;&gt;Should I rely on comparison rates to decide what loan is best?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No.  They are a guide only.  Speak to a professional mortgage broker who will undertake a detailed comparison of all features, benefits &amp;amp; costs to ensure you have accurate information to be able to make good financial decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">A comparison rate is a tool to help consumers identify the true cost of a loan by reducing the costs of a loan—including interest &amp;amp; fees—into a single percentage rate to easily compare the true cost of home loans. We can use comparison rates to compare various loans from different lenders.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-comparison-rates.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Top 5 useless tips to save a deposit</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/top-5-not-so-great-tips-to-save-a-deposit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Top 5 useless tips to save a deposit" /><published>2017-06-02T17:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-02T17:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/top-5-not-so-great-tips-to-save-a-deposit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/top-5-not-so-great-tips-to-save-a-deposit/">&lt;p&gt;According to a recent newspaper article if you earn $150,000 p/a you can save $100,000 deposit in just 2 years. This is fantastic if you earn that sort of dough.  So it got me thinking, what other fairy tale ideas have others published all in the name of helping you save for a deposit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Here are my top 5 not-so-great tips on how to save a deposit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;switch-off-the-lights&quot;&gt;Switch off the Lights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows this one, the old switch off the lights when not in use but seriously, one light bulb running for one hour costs about 0.2cents! The big idea here is to save on utility bills like electricity &amp;amp; phones etc. With effort you can potentially save 20% but this might only equate to $800 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;switch-your-savings-to-a-high-interest-account&quot;&gt;Switch your savings to a high interest account&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason you’re saving is that you don’t have any!  If you did have $10,000 though at 2% and switched to 4%, you will make an extra $200 p/a interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sell-stuff-on-ebay&quot;&gt;Sell stuff on Ebay&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’ve sold my 90’s CD collection, a $10 K-Mart t-shirt I got for my birthday and a set of old car seat covers.  So I now have an extra $38.53 saved!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drink-instant-coffee-instead-of-buying-a-coffee-on-the-way-to-work&quot;&gt;Drink instant coffee instead of buying a coffee on the way to work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 days a week, 48 weeks a year, $5 a coffee, that’s $1,200 in 12mths.  But instant coffee!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-a-2nd-job&quot;&gt;Get a 2nd Job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work a few extra hours each week in a 2nd job and make an extra $200, less tax that’s $7,000 a year.  Fantastic idea if jobs were readily available.  Reality is you’re unlikely to find a job paying $200 a wk and flexible to fit in with current employer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tips might be useful if you’re saving for that new TV but the last time I checked, a house is a little more expensive than a flatscreen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">According to a recent newspaper article if you earn $150,000 p/a you can save $100,000 deposit in just 2 years. This is fantastic if you earn that sort of dough.  So it got me thinking, what other fairy tale ideas have others published all in the name of helping you save for a deposit.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Genuine Savings Vs Non Genuine Savings</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/genuine-savings-vs-non-genuine-savings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Genuine Savings Vs Non Genuine Savings" /><published>2017-06-01T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-01T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/genuine-savings-vs-non-genuine-savings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/genuine-savings-vs-non-genuine-savings/">&lt;p&gt;Whether savings is genuine or non-genuine can sometimes make a difference between an approval or a decline but most of the time the biggest difference is more to do with the cost of mortgage insurance and the relevant interest rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;genuine-savings&quot;&gt;Genuine Savings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genuine Savings is an established savings pattern over a period of 3 months. Savings are considered genuine when:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Has come from any source and remained untouched in a bank account for a min 3 months or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sale of shares, if ownership of shares were for longer than 3 months or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proceeds from the sale of Real Estate where the borrower was an owner of the property being sold or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Redraw on an existing loan where the loan is in the borrowers name or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bonuses from an employer as long as bonus is not used as income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-genuine-savings&quot;&gt;Non Genuine Savings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non Genuine Savings is where the deposit has come from any other source that is not considered to be ‘Genuine’:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Home Owners Grant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gifts or Inheritances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Builder &amp;amp; vendor discounts or incentives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax Returns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sale of vehicle or asset other than property or shares&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Savings held in the name of a business or company&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Savings is borrowed from any source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-grey-area&quot;&gt;The grey area&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non Genuine savings can sometimes be treated as ‘Genuine’ in the following situations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Borrower can prove a reliable rental history with a licensed agent for at least 6mths with a lease in their own name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Borrower can prove extra repayments made on an existing loan (including personal loans) equals the amount of non-genuine savings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Borrower can prove with rates notice and loan statements, they have equity in an existing real estate property&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just because genuine savings is the preferred source for most lenders this does not mean borrowers cannot get a loan if their savings is non-genuine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having enough savings to begin with is more important than where it came from.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Whether savings is genuine or non-genuine can sometimes make a difference between an approval or a decline but most of the time the biggest difference is more to do with the cost of mortgage insurance and the relevant interest rate.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lender Review—Virgin Money</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lender-review-virgin-money/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lender Review—Virgin Money" /><published>2017-05-30T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-30T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lender-review-virgin-money</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lender-review-virgin-money/">&lt;p&gt;Virgin Money Australia is an Australian financial services company owned by Bank of Queensland, and has 150,000 customers. In 2003, Virgin Money was launched in Australia with the launch of Virgin Money credit cards. In 2013 Virgin Money Australia was bought by Bank of Queensland for $40 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-are-they&quot;&gt;Who are they?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the global Virgin brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;services&quot;&gt;Services?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Credit Cards, Insurance, Superannuation and recently Home Loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-owns-them&quot;&gt;Who owns them?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subsidiary of Bank of Queensland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-they-good-at&quot;&gt;What are they good at?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low deposit home loans &amp;amp; first home buyers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Velocity reward points&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No frills credit cards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lendfirst-comments&quot;&gt;Lendfirst Comments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new lender with a fresh approach to home loans, First Home Buyer Friendly. Credit policy is slightly restrictive i.e. will not accept any self-employed applicants and they do restrict the postcodes they lend in however the credit managers are experienced and genuinely do engage with the broker to find ways to get the loan approved. Velocity reward points program is market leading and credit card options are good. Offset is available but not designed to be client’s main transactional bank. Home loan rates and pricing are extremely competitive which can sometimes lead to delays. Virgin Money are not an option for self-employed or credit impaired clients or those wanting to construct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lendfirst-scorecard&quot;&gt;Lendfirst Scorecard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First home buyers ★★★★★&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upgraders ★★★★☆&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investors ★★★★☆&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Virgin Money Australia is an Australian financial services company owned by Bank of Queensland, and has 150,000 customers. In 2003, Virgin Money was launched in Australia with the launch of Virgin Money credit cards. In 2013 Virgin Money Australia was bought by Bank of Queensland for $40 million.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-lender-review-virgin-money.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lenders Mortgage Insurance—FAQ</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lenders-mortgage-insurance-faq/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lenders Mortgage Insurance—FAQ" /><published>2017-05-25T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-25T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lenders-mortgage-insurance-faq</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lenders-mortgage-insurance-faq/">&lt;p&gt;Lenders Mortgage Insurance is an insurance policy that pays the difference between the sale price of a property and the outstanding loan owed to a bank in the event of a forced sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, for a property sold at Mortgagee Auction for $340,000 with outstanding loan of $362,000, the claim amount is $22,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-does-it-cover&quot;&gt;Who does it cover?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy covers the Bank only.  Bank collects $340,000 at Auction and $22,000 from the Mortgage insurer.  The Insurer then takes action to recover $22,000 directly from the borrower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-pays-the-premium&quot;&gt;Who pays the premium?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The borrower. It is paid once only at the start of the loan.  It can be paid from borrower’s own savings or if lender allows, it can be added to the loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-do-i-need-to-have-it&quot;&gt;When do I need to have it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is at the banks discretion, but usually always applies if the loan is more than 80% of the security value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-much-does-it-cost&quot;&gt;How much does it cost?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premiums can range from $500 to $50,000 or more.  The premium is percentage based and this benchmark increases with risk and amount. For Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A $350,000 loan at 82% is approx. $2,300 but a $350,000 loan at 95% is approx. $12,000.

A $750,000 loan at 82% is approx. $6,900 but a $750,000 loan at 95% is approx. $35,000 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-i-add-the-premium-to-my-loan&quot;&gt;Can I add the premium to my loan?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, but most banks won’t if you are already borrowing 95% of the security value before adding the premium.  There are some lenders that allow it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-you-show-me-an-example&quot;&gt;Can you show me an example?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;95% Max&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;100% Max&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Purchase Price&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$370,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$370,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Base Loan Amount (95%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Premium Amount&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$12,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$12,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amount actually borrowed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$362,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Funds available from loan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$338,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Savings Needed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$32,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$20,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-i-get-a-refund-if-i-refinance&quot;&gt;Do I get a refund if I refinance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, you will have to pay the full amount again regardless of how long you have been with the previous lender. If you refinance with the same lender, you only pay the difference between any new premium and what you’ve already paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-the-mortgage-insurer-separate-to-the-bank&quot;&gt;Is the Mortgage Insurer separate to the bank?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most banks use either of the 2 main mortgage insurers in Australia, QBE and Genworth.  Some banks self-insure, which means they take on the risk themselves but still collect the mortgage insurance premium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-the-mortgage-insurer-decline-my-loan-if-the-bank-approves-it&quot;&gt;Can the Mortgage Insurer decline my loan if the Bank approves it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, but it is rare.  If it does happen, it is most likely due to an issue with the security, such as its location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-can-i-avoid-it&quot;&gt;How can I avoid it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a 20% deposit or find a guarantor who can offer extra security. Some occupations like doctors, engineers etc sometimes only have to pay when the loan is greater than 90%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-should-i-do-if-i-have-more-questions&quot;&gt;What should I do if I have more questions?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speak to a professional mortgage broker.  If your question is not answered here then it is likely you need to discuss the question with an expert.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Lenders Mortgage Insurance is an insurance policy that pays the difference between the sale price of a property and the outstanding loan owed to a bank in the event of a forced sale.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Explaining the RBA cash rate with donut theory</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/explaining-the-rba-cash-rate-with-donut-theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Explaining the RBA cash rate with donut theory" /><published>2017-05-22T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/explaining-the-rba-cash-rate-with-donut-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/explaining-the-rba-cash-rate-with-donut-theory/">&lt;p&gt;So the cost of donuts has gone up $0.50 but before you write to your local member of parliament demanding a royal commission let’s have a think about the costs that go into making a donut.  There’s yeast, cinnamon, oil, cream, jam, chocolate and the many other ingredients. If the cost of some or all of these ingredients increase, than it is logic and reality that the overall price we pay for the donut increases too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s assume the price of jam, cream &amp;amp; yeast are all controlled by the one supplier, let’s say this supplier is a government organisation charged with ensuring the health and well-being of all Australians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are eating too many donuts and risk becoming overweight &amp;amp; unhealthy, this organisation will increase the cost of jam, cream &amp;amp; yeast which will increase the price of donuts and we stop buying donuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If on the other hand we are not buying enough donuts, the donut making industry would cease to exist and thousands would be out of work so the supplier lowers the cost of jam, cream &amp;amp; yeast resulting in cheaper donuts and we buy more donuts allowing everyone to keep their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now assume the donut maker is a Bank, the government organisation is the Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) and the cash rate is jam, cream &amp;amp; yeast.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">So the cost of donuts has gone up $0.50 but before you write to your local member of parliament demanding a royal commission let’s have a think about the costs that go into making a donut. There’s yeast, cinnamon, oil, cream, jam, chocolate and the many other ingredients. If the cost of some or all of these ingredients increase, than it is logic and reality that the overall price we pay for the donut increases too.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-explaining-the-rba-cash-rate-with-donut-theory.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">100% Offset Account</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/100-percent-offset-account/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100% Offset Account" /><published>2017-05-19T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-19T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/100-percent-offset-account</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/100-percent-offset-account/">&lt;p&gt;A 100% Offset Account is a normal everyday transaction account that is linked to your home loan which can reduce the interest charged. A full offset means that 100% of the funds in your offset account will be deducted from what you owe on your home loan before interest is calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The run down on offset accounts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are transactional and can be used for salary credits, ATM &amp;amp; EFTPOS withdrawals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accessible with internet and phone banking just like any other savings or transaction account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They do not earn any interest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They have no minimum balance requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Must be an account held at the same bank as your home loan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Must be in exactly the same name as the home loan – If joint loan then must be joint savings account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usually only available with variable rate loans but a small number of banks allow them on fixed rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how 100% offset accounts work, you first need to understand &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-do-banks-calculate-interest/&quot;&gt;how banks calculate interest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the same example of $350,000 loan at 4.50% rate this time with $20,000 in a 100% offset account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Loan Balance – Offset Balance) X (Annual Rate/365) = Daily Interest
($350,000 - $20,000) X (4.50% / 365) = Daily Interest
$330,000 X 0.0123287% = Daily Interest 
$40.68 = Daily Interest
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is done every day.  At the end of a 30 day month, the total daily amounts $1,221 is debited to the loan so the loan balance becomes $351,221.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The normal monthly payment of $1,774 is still made and loan balance then starts day 1 of the next month at $349,447.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$349,447 - $20,000 X 0.0123287% = $40.62
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may not seem like much but you have saved $2.47 a day.  Over 12 months that’s a saving of approximately $900.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful, some offsets come with extra fees and higher rates. Here is a real example of the difference in one lenders products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;$350,000 Loan with $20,000 in Offset&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Basic no offset&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;With Offset&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Interest Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.10%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.65%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monthly Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$33&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Daily Interest&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$39.31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$44.59&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monthly Cost&lt;br /&gt;(interest + fees)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,179.30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,370.70&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monthly Offset Benefit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$76.44&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Net monthly cost&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,179.30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,294.26&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*$50,000 is the min balance needed to be better off with offset in this example&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example does not apply in all situations but it does highlight the potential downsides to 100% offset accounts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">A 100% Offset Account is a normal everyday transaction account that is linked to your home loan which can reduce the interest charged. A full offset means that 100% of the funds in your offset account will be deducted from what you owe on your home loan before interest is calculated.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry></feed>