<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-06-01T13:42:20+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/</id><title type="html">LendFirst Home Loans</title><subtitle>LendFirst offers smart advice and real solutions for first home buyers and first-time investors, in Cairns, Queeensland, Australia.</subtitle><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><entry><title type="html">Genuine Savings Vs Non Genuine Savings</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/genuine-savings-vs-non-genuine-savings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Genuine Savings Vs Non Genuine Savings" /><published>2017-06-01T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-01T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/genuine-savings-vs-non-genuine-savings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/genuine-savings-vs-non-genuine-savings/">&lt;p&gt;Whether savings is genuine or non-genuine can sometimes make a difference between an approval or a decline but most of the time the biggest difference is more to do with the cost of mortgage insurance and the relevant interest rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;genuine-savings&quot;&gt;Genuine Savings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genuine Savings is an established savings pattern over a period of 3 months. Savings are considered genuine when:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Has come from any source and remained untouched in a bank account for a min 3 months or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sale of shares, if ownership of shares were for longer than 3 months or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proceeds from the sale of Real Estate where the borrower was an owner of the property being sold or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Redraw on an existing loan where the loan is in the borrowers name or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bonuses from an employer as long as bonus is not used as income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-genuine-savings&quot;&gt;Non Genuine Savings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non Genuine Savings is where the deposit has come from any other source that is not considered to be ‘Genuine’:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Home Owners Grant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gifts or Inheritances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Builder &amp;amp; vendor discounts or incentives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax Returns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sale of vehicle or asset other than property or shares&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Savings held in the name of a business or company&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Savings is borrowed from any source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-grey-area&quot;&gt;The grey area&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non Genuine savings can sometimes be treated as ‘Genuine’ in the following situations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Borrower can prove a reliable rental history with a licensed agent for at least 6mths with a lease in their own name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Borrower can prove extra repayments made on an existing loan (including personal loans) equals the amount of non-genuine savings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Borrower can prove with rates notice and loan statements, they have equity in an existing real estate property&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just because genuine savings is the preferred source for most lenders this does not mean borrowers cannot get a loan if their savings is non-genuine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having enough savings to begin with is more important than where it came from.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Whether savings is genuine or non-genuine can sometimes make a difference between an approval or a decline but most of the time the biggest difference is more to do with the cost of mortgage insurance and the relevant interest rate.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lender Review—Virgin Money</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lender-review-virgin-money/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lender Review—Virgin Money" /><published>2017-05-30T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-30T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lender-review-virgin-money</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lender-review-virgin-money/">&lt;p&gt;Virgin Money Australia is an Australian financial services company owned by Bank of Queensland, and has 150,000 customers. In 2003, Virgin Money was launched in Australia with the launch of Virgin Money credit cards. In 2013 Virgin Money Australia was bought by Bank of Queensland for $40 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-are-they&quot;&gt;Who are they?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the global Virgin brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;services&quot;&gt;Services?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Credit Cards, Insurance, Superannuation and recently Home Loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-owns-them&quot;&gt;Who owns them?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subsidiary of Bank of Queensland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-they-good-at&quot;&gt;What are they good at?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low deposit home loans &amp;amp; first home buyers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Velocity reward points&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No frills credit cards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lendfirst-comments&quot;&gt;Lendfirst Comments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new lender with a fresh approach to home loans, First Home Buyer Friendly. Credit policy is slightly restrictive i.e. will not accept any self-employed applicants and they do restrict the postcodes they lend in however the credit managers are experienced and genuinely do engage with the broker to find ways to get the loan approved. Velocity reward points program is market leading and credit card options are good. Offset is available but not designed to be client’s main transactional bank. Home loan rates and pricing are extremely competitive which can sometimes lead to delays. Virgin Money are not an option for self-employed or credit impaired clients or those wanting to construct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lendfirst-scorecard&quot;&gt;Lendfirst Scorecard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First home buyers ★★★★★&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upgraders ★★★★☆&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investors ★★★★☆&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Virgin Money Australia is an Australian financial services company owned by Bank of Queensland, and has 150,000 customers. In 2003, Virgin Money was launched in Australia with the launch of Virgin Money credit cards. In 2013 Virgin Money Australia was bought by Bank of Queensland for $40 million.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-lender-review-virgin-money.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lenders Mortgage Insurance—FAQ</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lenders-mortgage-insurance-faq/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lenders Mortgage Insurance—FAQ" /><published>2017-05-25T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-25T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lenders-mortgage-insurance-faq</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lenders-mortgage-insurance-faq/">&lt;p&gt;Lenders Mortgage Insurance is an insurance policy that pays the difference between the sale price of a property and the outstanding loan owed to a bank in the event of a forced sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, for a property sold at Mortgagee Auction for $340,000 with outstanding loan of $362,000, the claim amount is $22,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-does-it-cover&quot;&gt;Who does it cover?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy covers the Bank only.  Bank collects $340,000 at Auction and $22,000 from the Mortgage insurer.  The Insurer then takes action to recover $22,000 directly from the borrower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-pays-the-premium&quot;&gt;Who pays the premium?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The borrower. It is paid once only at the start of the loan.  It can be paid from borrower’s own savings or if lender allows, it can be added to the loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-do-i-need-to-have-it&quot;&gt;When do I need to have it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is at the banks discretion, but usually always applies if the loan is more than 80% of the security value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-much-does-it-cost&quot;&gt;How much does it cost?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premiums can range from $500 to $50,000 or more.  The premium is percentage based and this benchmark increases with risk and amount. For Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A $350,000 loan at 82% is approx. $2,300 but a $350,000 loan at 95% is approx. $12,000.

A $750,000 loan at 82% is approx. $6,900 but a $750,000 loan at 95% is approx. $35,000 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-i-add-the-premium-to-my-loan&quot;&gt;Can I add the premium to my loan?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, but most banks won’t if you are already borrowing 95% of the security value before adding the premium.  There are some lenders that allow it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-you-show-me-an-example&quot;&gt;Can you show me an example?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;95% Max&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;100% Max&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Purchase Price&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$370,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$370,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Base Loan Amount (95%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Premium Amount&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$12,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$12,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amount actually borrowed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$362,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Funds available from loan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$338,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Savings Needed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$32,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$20,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-i-get-a-refund-if-i-refinance&quot;&gt;Do I get a refund if I refinance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, you will have to pay the full amount again regardless of how long you have been with the previous lender. If you refinance with the same lender, you only pay the difference between any new premium and what you’ve already paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-the-mortgage-insurer-separate-to-the-bank&quot;&gt;Is the Mortgage Insurer separate to the bank?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most banks use either of the 2 main mortgage insurers in Australia, QBE and Genworth.  Some banks self-insure, which means they take on the risk themselves but still collect the mortgage insurance premium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-the-mortgage-insurer-decline-my-loan-if-the-bank-approves-it&quot;&gt;Can the Mortgage Insurer decline my loan if the Bank approves it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, but it is rare.  If it does happen, it is most likely due to an issue with the security, such as its location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-can-i-avoid-it&quot;&gt;How can I avoid it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a 20% deposit or find a guarantor who can offer extra security. Some occupations like doctors, engineers etc sometimes only have to pay when the loan is greater than 90%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-should-i-do-if-i-have-more-questions&quot;&gt;What should I do if I have more questions?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speak to a professional mortgage broker.  If your question is not answered here then it is likely you need to discuss the question with an expert.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Lenders Mortgage Insurance is an insurance policy that pays the difference between the sale price of a property and the outstanding loan owed to a bank in the event of a forced sale.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Explaining the RBA cash rate with donut theory</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/explaining-the-rba-cash-rate-with-donut-theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Explaining the RBA cash rate with donut theory" /><published>2017-05-22T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/explaining-the-rba-cash-rate-with-donut-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/explaining-the-rba-cash-rate-with-donut-theory/">&lt;p&gt;So the cost of donuts has gone up $0.50 but before you write to your local member of parliament demanding a royal commission let’s have a think about the costs that go into making a donut.  There’s yeast, cinnamon, oil, cream, jam, chocolate and the many other ingredients. If the cost of some or all of these ingredients increase, than it is logic and reality that the overall price we pay for the donut increases too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s assume the price of jam, cream &amp;amp; yeast are all controlled by the one supplier, let’s say this supplier is a government organisation charged with ensuring the health and well-being of all Australians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are eating too many donuts and risk becoming overweight &amp;amp; unhealthy, this organisation will increase the cost of jam, cream &amp;amp; yeast which will increase the price of donuts and we stop buying donuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If on the other hand we are not buying enough donuts, the donut making industry would cease to exist and thousands would be out of work so the supplier lowers the cost of jam, cream &amp;amp; yeast resulting in cheaper donuts and we buy more donuts allowing everyone to keep their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now assume the donut maker is a Bank, the government organisation is the Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) and the cash rate is jam, cream &amp;amp; yeast.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">So the cost of donuts has gone up $0.50 but before you write to your local member of parliament demanding a royal commission let’s have a think about the costs that go into making a donut. There’s yeast, cinnamon, oil, cream, jam, chocolate and the many other ingredients. If the cost of some or all of these ingredients increase, than it is logic and reality that the overall price we pay for the donut increases too.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-explaining-the-rba-cash-rate-with-donut-theory.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">100% Offset Account</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/100-percent-offset-account/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100% Offset Account" /><published>2017-05-19T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-19T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/100-percent-offset-account</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/100-percent-offset-account/">&lt;p&gt;A 100% Offset Account is a normal everyday transaction account that is linked to your home loan which can reduce the interest charged. A full offset means that 100% of the funds in your offset account will be deducted from what you owe on your home loan before interest is calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The run down on offset accounts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are transactional and can be used for salary credits, ATM &amp;amp; EFTPOS withdrawals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accessible with internet and phone banking just like any other savings or transaction account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They do not earn any interest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They have no minimum balance requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Must be an account held at the same bank as your home loan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Must be in exactly the same name as the home loan – If joint loan then must be joint savings account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usually only available with variable rate loans but a small number of banks allow them on fixed rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how 100% offset accounts work, you first need to understand &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-do-banks-calculate-interest/&quot;&gt;how banks calculate interest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the same example of $350,000 loan at 4.50% rate this time with $20,000 in a 100% offset account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Loan Balance – Offset Balance) X (Annual Rate/365) = Daily Interest
($350,000 - $20,000) X (4.50% / 365) = Daily Interest
$330,000 X 0.0123287% = Daily Interest 
$40.68 = Daily Interest
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is done every day.  At the end of a 30 day month, the total daily amounts $1,221 is debited to the loan so the loan balance becomes $351,221.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The normal monthly payment of $1,774 is still made and loan balance then starts day 1 of the next month at $349,447.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$349,447 - $20,000 X 0.0123287% = $40.62
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may not seem like much but you have saved $2.47 a day.  Over 12 months that’s a saving of approximately $900.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful, some offsets come with extra fees and higher rates. Here is a real example of the difference in one lenders products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;$350,000 Loan with $20,000 in Offset&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Basic no offset&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;With Offset&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Interest Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.10%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.65%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monthly Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$33&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Daily Interest&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$39.31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$44.59&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monthly Cost&lt;br /&gt;(interest + fees)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,179.30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,370.70&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monthly Offset Benefit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$76.44&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Net monthly cost&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,179.30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,294.26&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*$50,000 is the min balance needed to be better off with offset in this example&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example does not apply in all situations but it does highlight the potential downsides to 100% offset accounts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">A 100% Offset Account is a normal everyday transaction account that is linked to your home loan which can reduce the interest charged. A full offset means that 100% of the funds in your offset account will be deducted from what you owe on your home loan before interest is calculated.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Focus on the fine print</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/focus-on-the-fine-print/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Focus on the fine print" /><published>2017-05-15T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-15T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/focus-on-the-fine-print</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/focus-on-the-fine-print/">&lt;p&gt;Being a keen angler, I’m always on the lookout for new fishing gear.  Spotting a facebook ad for a fishing shop ‘Closing Down – 50% off everything’ sale got my interest with no ‘Upto’ clause inserted. I checked the bank balance, worked out how to explain it to my wife and jumped online credit card in hand and they didn’t disappoint, there were bargains galore and thanked the fishing gods for my good fortune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding the bargains to my cart I went to checkout but there was no section for postage. Confused I read the fine print to discover the discount only applied to store pick up.  No good when you live 2,500klms away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen banks, brokers and online lenders advertise home loans in a similar way.  Cheap rates are advertised and all are genuine, but reading the fine print they are only available to certain borrowers.  Some only apply to those with 30% deposits, some to capital cities and almost none for small deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing 35+ lenders, there are over 5,000 different interest rate variations all with different requirements.  Do not make decisions based on an advertised interest rate.  There is no point making key life decisions on a cheap rate you saw on facebook if you do not qualify for it.
The fine print is the key determining factor of your interest rate and the fine print is now changing faster than it ever has before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t ignore rates completely, just don’t make big life decisions based on them alone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Being a keen angler, I’m always on the lookout for new fishing gear. Spotting a facebook ad for a fishing shop ‘Closing Down – 50% off everything’ sale got my interest with no ‘Upto’ clause inserted. I checked the bank balance, worked out how to explain it to my wife and jumped online credit card in hand and they didn’t disappoint, there were bargains galore and thanked the fishing gods for my good fortune.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-focus-on-the-fine-print.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How do Banks calculate interest?</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/how-do-banks-calculate-interest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How do Banks calculate interest?" /><published>2017-05-11T11:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-11T11:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/how-do-banks-calculate-interest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/how-do-banks-calculate-interest/">&lt;p&gt;Home loan rates are shown as an annual rate but are divided by 365 to get a daily rate (use 366 for a leap year). The daily rate is then applied to the loan balance each day. Assume a $350,000 loan with an interest rate of 4.50%. Figures are rounded for ease of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Loan Balance X (Annual Rate/365) = Daily Interest
$350,000 X (4.50% / 365) = Daily Interest
$350,000 X 0.0123287% = Daily Interest
$43.15 = Daily Interest
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This calculation is done every day. At the end of a 30 day month, the total $1,294 is debited to the loan so the balance becomes $351,294.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually on this day the monthly payment of $1,774 is made and the loan balance starts day 1 of the next month at $349,520 and the process starts again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$349,521 X 0.0123287% = $43.09
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same calculation applies regardless of whether the loan is a fixed or variable rate. If the loan settles on say 13th of the month, it is the number of days until the 13th of the next month and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding this process is critical in deciding which loan features (redraws, offsets) and repayment options (weekly, fortnightly, monthly) work best.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Home loan rates are shown as an annual rate but are divided by 365 to get a daily rate (use 366 for a leap year). The daily rate is then applied to the loan balance each day. Assume a $350,000 loan with an interest rate of 4.50%. Figures are rounded for ease of understanding.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing Lendfirst Home Loans, the low deposit experts</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/introducing-lendfirst-home-loans-the-low-deposit-experts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Lendfirst Home Loans, the low deposit experts" /><published>2017-05-08T11:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-08T11:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/introducing-lendfirst-home-loans-the-low-deposit-experts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/introducing-lendfirst-home-loans-the-low-deposit-experts/">&lt;p&gt;Lendfirst Home Loans (previously Australian Property Finance, Cairns) purpose is to assist undervalued low deposit and first home buyers find real solutions to buy their homes. First home buyers and low deposit buyers are regularly mislead by media, friends, family, banks and other advisers who say home ownership is not possible without a large deposit. This is simply not the case and many miss out because they listen to incorrect advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a first home buyer or have a limited deposit, Lendfirst Home Loans specialises in finding real solutions just for you.  Because we are experts in low deposit loans, we often get you a ‘Yes’ when others have already given you a ‘No’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will publish regular thought provoking and interesting articles via our weekly blog and provide regular informative explanations of policies, processes and systems needed to buy a house and/or get a home loan. Follow us on Facebook, visit our website or simply email to participate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Lendfirst Home Loans (previously Australian Property Finance, Cairns) purpose is to assist undervalued low deposit and first home buyers find real solutions to buy their homes. First home buyers and low deposit buyers are regularly mislead by media, friends, family, banks and other advisers who say home ownership is not possible without a large deposit. This is simply not the case and many miss out because they listen to incorrect advice.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-introducing-lendfirst-home-loans,-the-low-deposit-experts.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">An unsuccessful debt reduction strategy</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/unsuccessful-debt-reduction-strategy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An unsuccessful debt reduction strategy" /><published>2016-09-04T23:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2016-09-04T23:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/unsuccessful-debt-reduction-strategy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/unsuccessful-debt-reduction-strategy/">&lt;p&gt;A client of mine, who we shall call Bob, earned an obscenely high amount of income, he drove a brand new BMW, always wore nice Italian suits and travelled overseas at least twice a year.  Ignoring stereotypes, Bob was actually a very down to earth, genuine nice guy but terrible with money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, he was advised to change his home loan to a revolving line of credit and open a credit card.  He was to put his salary into the line of credit and spend on the credit card.  At the end of the month he would transfer the credit card balance in full from the line of credit thus avoiding interest on the credit card and saving $100’s in interest on the home loan during the month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds great in theory however the one big flaw was the credit card limit the adviser gave Bob.  The limit on Bob’s credit card equalled his net monthly income so Bob being the spendthrift he was, blew his credit card limit every month and surprise surprise Bob’s home loan balance never reduced a cent in over 5yrs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve Bob’s problem, we first changed his home loan to a term loan with principal and interest repayments.  Not only did this give Bob a firm structure and plan to reduce his loan balance he also saved a bit of interest in the process as revolving line of credit facilities are more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we found a loan that had a full 100% offset included.  When used properly, this feature has the same benefit as a line of credit but forces the loan to reduce to zero after 30yrs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we reviewed Bob’s household budget and reduced his credit card limit to equal his monthly expenses not his monthly income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Utilising the same strategy as the previous adviser but with a different product and credit card limit in place Bob can now actually start paying his loan off sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to report that Bob has paid his loan off in under 5yrs but that would be a lie.  Bob couldn’t help himself and continues to spend like crazy but at least now his loan is reducing every month and each month he is building more and more equity in his home in the hope that one day, he will spend his money on something more useful, like an investment property perhaps!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><category term="problem solved" /><category term="debt" /><summary type="html">A client of mine, who we shall call Bob, earned an obscenely high amount of income, he drove a brand new BMW, always wore nice Italian suits and travelled overseas at least twice a year. Ignoring stereotypes, Bob was actually a very down to earth, genuine nice guy but terrible with money.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-an-unsuccessful-debt-reduction-strategy.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">5 reasons why pre-approvals are bad</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/5-reasons-why-pre-approvals-are-bad-for-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 reasons why pre-approvals are bad" /><published>2016-08-29T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2016-08-29T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/5-reasons-why-pre-approvals-are-bad-for-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/5-reasons-why-pre-approvals-are-bad-for-you/">&lt;p&gt;A pre-approval of finance before shopping for a house is common for many buyers and recommended by many lending experts but applying for a pre-approval could ruin your chances when it comes to making a formal application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top 5 reasons why a pre-approval is bad for you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-they-expire-after-90days&quot;&gt;1. They expire after 90days&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 90days you start from scratch again. A new application form and fresh information on everything you already provided is needed.  Even after 30 days, most lenders still require fresh payslips, bank statements etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-it-is-not-a-full-assessment&quot;&gt;2. It is not a full assessment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre-approvals have so many conditions in the fine print, they are practically a worthless piece of paper.  With most lenders, payslips are not checked, bank statements are not verified and mortgage insurers are never asked for approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-no-protection-against-policy-changes&quot;&gt;3. No protection against policy changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a lender changes policies during the 90days, the new policy will be enforced.  This happened in 2015 when thousands of investors were caught out by banks increasing minimum deposits for investors.  Many lost $1,000’s in deposits and fees because they relied upon a pre-approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-can-ruin-credit-historys&quot;&gt;4. Can ruin credit history’s&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time a lender does a pre-approval, an enquiry is made on your credit file. If you have multiple pre-approvals even with the same lender this will negatively impact on your credit.  This could result in a formal application being declined because the credit file is too ‘busy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-its-a-sneaky-sales-trick&quot;&gt;5. It’s a sneaky sales trick&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industry encourages pre-approvals because it stops buyers shopping around. Buyers can get locked into a bad deal because they can’t go to another lender as their credit file is now too busy and can only go with the lender who issued the original pre-approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some circumstances, a pre-approval can be extremely beneficial and is the best course of action for some applicants however for the most part, speaking with a highly trained and experienced mortgage broker can often give the buyer just as much confidence to make an offer without impacting on credit files or missing out on a really good deal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><category term="borrowing" /><summary type="html">A pre-approval of finance before shopping for a house is common for many buyers and recommended by many lending experts but applying for a pre-approval could ruin your chances when it comes to making a formal application.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-5-reasons-why-pre-approvals-are-bad.jpg" /></entry></feed>