<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-17T22:09:04+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/</id><title type="html">LendFirst Home Loans</title><subtitle>LendFirst offers smart advice and real solutions for first home buyers and first-time investors, in Cairns, Queeensland, Australia.</subtitle><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><entry><title type="html">Donate to charity? You might have a gambling problem!</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/donation-gambling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Donate to charity? You might have a gambling problem!" /><published>2017-08-16T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-08-16T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/donation-gambling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/donation-gambling/">&lt;p&gt;A client of mine, who regularly donated to charity for over 20 years, got a rude shock last week when a bank’s statement scanning software identified the client as a potential gambler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The client’s honest intention was simply to make a $10 donation each month to charity however that donation took the form of a $10 endeavour lottery ticket. Unfortunately, the word ‘Lotteries’ appears on his statement. The software identifies the word Lotteries showing up on a regular basis and therefore flagged a potential gambling problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll be pleased to know the clients ‘gambling addiction’ was thoroughly explained and eventually ignored but it did create unnecessary delays and anxiety for the client and his broker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As banks continue to utilise technology to speed up processing times the human element and common sense is becoming obsolete but get used to it because it’s here to stay. 
So before you apply for your next loan, look over your statements to see what nasty habits you’ve been getting yourself into to, because if you don’t, the bank will!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">A client of mine, who regularly donated to charity for over 20 years, got a rude shock last week when a bank’s statement scanning software identified the client as a potential gambler.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Important Contract Clauses (Qld)—Finance Date</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/important-contract-clauses-finance-date/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Important Contract Clauses (Qld)—Finance Date" /><published>2017-08-11T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-08-11T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/important-contract-clauses-finance-date</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/important-contract-clauses-finance-date/">&lt;p&gt;In Queensland, the Finance Date Contract Clauses refer to the period of time a buyer has to obtain formal finance approval for the purchase after entering a contract to buy a property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-does-it-exist&quot;&gt;Why does it exist?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give banks and lenders the time they need to formally assess the borrower and that the property is acceptable security for a loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-long-does-it-last-for&quot;&gt;How long does it last for?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry standard is approaching 21 days (includes weekends and public holidays) but it can be any period of time agreed to by both the buyer and the seller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-day-does-it-start&quot;&gt;What day does it start?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day the contract is dated regardless of whether this is a business day or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-does-it-end&quot;&gt;When does it end?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 5pm on the day noted in the finance clause. If this is a non-business day, the expiry date carries forward to the next business day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-the-buyer-have-to-do-during-the-finance-period&quot;&gt;What does the buyer have to do during the finance period?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a formal application for a loan with your broker. Need to supply all documents including payslips, statements of savings etc etc. The bank needs to undertake a full assessment of this information and in most cases will also arrange an independent valuer to value the property. Once the bank issues a formal letter of approval, forward this letter immediately to your solicitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-i-change-my-mind-about-the-contract-during-the-finance-period&quot;&gt;Can I change my mind about the contract during the finance period?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. That is what the cooling off period was for. You must make all reasonable efforts to secure finance on or before finance expiry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-if-my-finance-is-declined&quot;&gt;What if my finance is declined?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Send a copy of the decline letter to your solicitor who will advise the seller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-if-i-need-more-time&quot;&gt;What if I need more time?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let your solicitor know immediately. They can request the seller extend the expiry date to give you more time. The seller can however refuse the request and you could potentially miss out on the property. Never assume finance extensions will be granted and never delay the loan application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-there-a-finance-clause-when-purchasing-at-an-auction&quot;&gt;Is there a finance clause when purchasing at an Auction?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. When buying at Auction, it is assumed you have sufficient finances available prior to bidding. In most cases lenders will not be able to provide an unconditional finance approval for a property prior to the purchase because they cannot assess whether that property is acceptable security for a loan until after the Auction. It is highly recommended you speak to your broker prior to bidding at Auction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">In Queensland, the Finance Date Contract Clauses refer to the period of time a buyer has to obtain formal finance approval for the purchase after entering a contract to buy a property.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Can online dating improve your loan application?</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/can-online-dating-improve-your-loan-application/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can online dating improve your loan application?" /><published>2017-07-27T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/Can-online-dating-improve-your-loan-application</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/can-online-dating-improve-your-loan-application/">&lt;p&gt;First Home Buyer but still single?  Hit the online dating scene to improve your chances of getting a loan. It’s simple mathematics, 1 person applying for a loan, 1 income but 2 people applying for a loan, 2 incomes.  The higher the income the higher the chance of an approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single person earning $40k a year with a good deposit might only be able to borrow $250k but a couple earning $80k a year with a smaller deposit might be able to borrow $500k.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you have it, it’s not this size of the deposit that counts, it’s what you do with your income that matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still single, try these one liners to help improve your loan application…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roses are Red, Violets are Blue, I’m not too adhesive but I’ll stick to you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Is your name Gillette? Because you’re the best a man can get! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your name Ariel? Because we Mermaid for each other! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were a triangle, you’d be acute one! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your name WiFi? Because I’m really feeling a connection!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">First Home Buyer but still single? Hit the online dating scene to improve your chances of getting a loan. It’s simple mathematics, 1 person applying for a loan, 1 income but 2 people applying for a loan, 2 incomes. The higher the income the higher the chance of an approval.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-lender-review-liberty-financial.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lender Review—Liberty Financial</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lender-review-liberty-financial/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lender Review—Liberty Financial" /><published>2017-07-19T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-07-19T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lender-review-liberty-financial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/lender-review-liberty-financial/">&lt;p&gt;Founded in 1997, Liberty Financial provides a wide range of loans for your home, your car and business, as well as investments and products from other financial institutions. Liberty Financial are an alternative that offers innovative solutions at competitive prices and more choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-are-they&quot;&gt;Who are they?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An independent specialist finance company&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;services&quot;&gt;Services?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Home Loans, car loans and business loans&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-owns-them&quot;&gt;Who owns them?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privately owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-they-good-at&quot;&gt;What are they good at?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low deposit home loans &amp;amp; first home buyers &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Borrowers that don’t meet standard bank criteria&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small businesses who need flexible credit policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lendfirst-comments&quot;&gt;Lendfirst Comments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lender with a broad range of credit policies to cover most situations, First Home Buyer Friendly and are market leading when borrowers have low deposits and non genuine savings. Traditional bank products are competitively priced and a good alternative to mainstream banks.  Liberty are best when mainstream banks say no.  Their custom product suite accepts clients with credit defaults, unusual income and many other credit impairments.  There are postcode restrictions and they place a high importance on good quality security in larger towns and cities.  They apply a common sense approach to credit and service is good whilst terms and conditions are easy to understand.  There is no branch network and Liberty is not recommended if you want a lender that does everything including credit cards, insurances, transaction accounts etc. They have access to private funders who can provide short term business funding to small business owners who need fast flexible solutions such as loans with no income declarations or verifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lendfirst-scorecard&quot;&gt;Lendfirst Scorecard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First home buyers ★★★★★&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upgraders ★★★☆☆&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investors ★★★☆☆&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Credit impaired ★★★★★&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small business ★★★★☆&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Founded in 1997, Liberty Financial provides a wide range of loans for your home, your car and business, as well as investments and products from other financial institutions. Liberty Financial are an alternative that offers innovative solutions at competitive prices and more choice.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-lender-review-liberty-financial.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Your Credit File</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/understanding-your-credit-file/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Your Credit File" /><published>2017-07-12T09:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-07-12T09:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/understanding-your-credit-file</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/understanding-your-credit-file/">&lt;p&gt;Your Credit File is a report held with a credit reporting body (Equifax, Dun &amp;amp; Bradstreet or Experian) that contains information relating to your credit history. If you have ever applied for a loan or credit, it is likely this information will be on your report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-loan-or-credit&quot;&gt;What is a loan or credit?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any personal loan, home loan, credit card are all types of credit that are reported. Can include mobile phone contracts, gas and electricity contracts, store accounts &amp;amp; equipment rentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-type-of-information-is-held&quot;&gt;What type of information is held?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any credit enquiries that is a loan or credit, any defaults either paid or not paid, public record information such as bankruptcies, court judgements, directorships &amp;amp; proprietorships, monthly repayment history on loans or credit (not all lenders currently supply this information)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-credit-enquiry&quot;&gt;What is a credit enquiry?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An application for a loan or credit regardless of whether the application was approved, declined, withdrawn or did not proceed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-credit-default&quot;&gt;What is a credit default?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where a loan or credit for $150 or more was/is more than 60 days overdue and the credit provider has tried to contact you they may lodge a default on your file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-bankruptcy&quot;&gt;What is a Bankruptcy?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Includes formal bankruptcy, debt agreements and personal insolvency. Applies when you are unable to pay all of your debts when they become due. Acts of bankruptcy are lodged on your file only after an extensive legal process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-long-is-information-kept-on-file&quot;&gt;How long is information kept on file?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All credit enquiries are held on your report for 5 years. Most credit defaults are held on file for 5 years also however some may last up to 7 years depending on how the credit provider recorded the default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-credit-enquiries-be-removed&quot;&gt;Can credit enquiries be removed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No – however sometimes a lender can request an enquiry be removed from your file if that enquiry was made in error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-credit-defaults-be-removed&quot;&gt;Can Credit Defaults be removed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No – however if you dispute the default either yourself or through a credit repair agency and the dispute is successful, the credit provider may remove the default as part of the dispute process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-acts-of-bankruptcy-be-removed&quot;&gt;Can acts of Bankruptcy be removed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-can-access-my-credit-file&quot;&gt;Who can access my credit file?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credit Providers, Mortgage Insurers, Trade Insurers and anyone else authorised to act on your behalf. The Privacy Act provides strong protections around who can access your credit file as not just anyone can get access to your credit report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-i-get-a-copy-of-my-report&quot;&gt;Can I get a copy of my report?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. You are entitled to 1 free credit report every year. This report does not contain your ‘Credit Score’ however for a cost you can receive a copy of your report with your score included. Visit www.mycreditfile.com.au to find out more and to order your report.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Your Credit File is a report held with a credit reporting body (Equifax, Dun &amp;amp; Bradstreet or Experian) that contains information relating to your credit history. If you have ever applied for a loan or credit, it is likely this information will be on your report.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How many Avocado Smashes would $20,000 buy?</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/how-many-avocado-smashes-would-20000-buy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How many Avocado Smashes would $20,000 buy?" /><published>2017-07-05T19:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-07-05T19:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/how-many-avocado-smashes-would-$20000-buy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/how-many-avocado-smashes-would-20000-buy/">&lt;p&gt;For those that missed the punchline, an Australian millionaire recently suggested millennials stop buying an Avocado Smash to save for a house deposit and his comments went viral around the globe (read the article &lt;a href=&quot;www.news.com.au/finance/money/costs/avocado-toast-mortgages-have-gone-global/news-story/0e691bfafc89e2d1511a7cbdfd074e9c&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Now that the Queensland First Home Buyers Grant of $20,000 has been extended until 31st December 2017, I wondered how long it would take to save $20,000 if I stopped buying avocado on toast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, 9 years… Assuming I paid $22 for an Avocado smash and I had one twice a week, every week of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There could be an easier way if you are a First Home Buyer. Some lenders may let you ‘pretend’ the $20,000 grant is your own savings so if your ‘real’ savings is small, buying or building your First Home today might just be possible. The lending criteria is very complex and you should speak to a mortgage broker who specialises in First Home Buyers as the wrong advice could mean the difference between owning your own home or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the main requirements to qualify for the government $20k grant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must be buying or building a ‘Brand New’ home under $750,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You or your spouse must not have previously owned property in Australia before&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must live in the house as your primary residence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must be 18yrs old&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must be an Australian Citizen or Permanent Resident (or applying with someone who is)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://firsthomeowners.initiatives.qld.gov.au/&quot;&gt;Queensland First Home Owners Grant&lt;/a&gt; or contact the Qld Office of State Revenue directly on 1300 300 734 to find out if you are eligible before considering or discussing your finance options.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">For those that missed the punchline, an Australian millionaire recently suggested millennials stop buying an Avocado Smash to save for a house deposit and his comments went viral around the globe (read the article here). Now that the Queensland First Home Buyers Grant of $20,000 has been extended until 31st December 2017, I wondered how long it would take to save $20,000 if I stopped buying avocado on toast.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-how-many-avocado-smashes-would-$20000-buy.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Important Contract Clauses—Cooling Off Period</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/important-contract-clauses-cooling-off-period/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Important Contract Clauses—Cooling Off Period" /><published>2017-06-27T20:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-27T20:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/important-contract-clauses-cooling-off-period</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/important-contract-clauses-cooling-off-period/">&lt;p&gt;The Cooling Off Period is the period after a buyer enters a contract to buy home or land in which the buyer can terminate the contract without having to provide a reason or justification to the seller. Notification must be provided in writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-long-does-it-last-for&quot;&gt;How long does it last for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 business days&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-day-does-it-start&quot;&gt;What day does it start?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day the buyer receives a signed contract executed by all parties.  If this day is a weekend, the cooling off period starts from the next business day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-does-it-end&quot;&gt;When does it end?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 5pm on the 5th day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;are-there-costs&quot;&gt;Are there costs?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seller has the right to charge the buyer a penalty of 0.25% of the purchase price.  If a larger deposit has been paid, then the balance of the deposit must be returned to the buyer within 14days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-the-buyer-waive-the-cooling-off-period&quot;&gt;Can the buyer waive the cooling off period?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes but it must be provided in writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-the-seller-waive-the-cooling-off-period&quot;&gt;Can the seller waive the cooling off period?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-exempt-from-a-cooling-off-clause&quot;&gt;What is exempt from a cooling off clause?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A contract where the property is purchased at auction or is purchased before 5pm the day after the auction and the buyer was a registered bidder.  Some other exclusions apply however these should be discussed with your legal representative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above information is general in nature and does not constitute legal advice.  This information has been summarised from and can be viewed in full at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.qld.gov.au/law/laws-regulated-industries-and-accountability/queensland-laws-and-regulations/regulated-industries-and-licensing/regulated-industries-licensing-and-legislation/property-industry-regulation/legal-requirements-for-the-property-industry/cooling-off-period-for-residential-property-contracts/&quot;&gt;the Queensland Government website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is strongly recommended buyers and sellers seek legal advice to answer any questions about their individual circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">The Cooling Off Period is the period after a buyer enters a contract to buy home or land in which the buyer can terminate the contract without having to provide a reason or justification to the seller. Notification must be provided in writing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Family BBQs are the First Home Buyer’s worst enemy</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/family-bbqs-are-the-first-home-buyers-worst-enemy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Family BBQs are the First Home Buyer's worst enemy" /><published>2017-06-20T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-20T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/family-bbqs-are-the%20first-home-buyers-worst-enemy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/family-bbqs-are-the-first-home-buyers-worst-enemy/">&lt;p&gt;What would happen if we re-plumbed the house on advice from a doctor or if we committed to surgery on the advice of a driving instructor and what would happen if we learnt how to drive on the advice from a plumber?  Sounds crazy I know but we do this all the time and we don’t realise it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone understands that to put in a new toilet, we speak to a plumber or to have surgery we chat to a doctor and the best person to teach us how to drive is a driving instructor but why do we continually follow the advice of parents, brothers, sisters and friends when it comes to home loan advice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge for a mortgage broker, is explaining to borrowers, particularly first home buyers why a specific bank, product or loan feature worked for their parents but won’t for them.  It usually stems from a conversation ending with the words “this worked really well for us, you should do it to!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it did work well but not everyone has the same income, deposit or credit history and just because it worked well for someone else, doesn’t mean it will for you.
Unless your parents, family &amp;amp; friends are mortgage brokers, acknowledge their opinion but please, do yourself a favour and follow advice from the people most qualified to give it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">What would happen if we re-plumbed the house on advice from a doctor or if we committed to surgery on the advice of a driving instructor and what would happen if we learnt how to drive on the advice from a plumber? Sounds crazy I know but we do this all the time and we don’t realise it!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Comparison rates</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/comparison-rates/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Comparison rates" /><published>2017-06-13T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-13T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/comparison-rates</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/comparison-rates/">&lt;p&gt;A comparison rate is a tool to help consumers identify the true cost of a loan by reducing the costs of a loan—including interest &amp;amp; fees—into a single percentage rate to easily compare the true cost of home loans.  We can use comparison rates to compare various loans from different lenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-we-have-them&quot;&gt;Why do we have them?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reveal any hidden costs or charges associated with a home loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-are-they-calculated&quot;&gt;How are they calculated?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application Fees and ongoing fees are reduced to a single percentage rate and added to the actual rate for comparison. If a loan has no fees the comparison rate should be the same as the actual rate. Here’s an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lender A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lender B&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amount&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Term&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30yrs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30yrs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Actual Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.24%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.39%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Application Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$600&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$600&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$395 per year&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Comparison Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.42%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.41%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-lender-b-is-the-better-option-then&quot;&gt;So Lender B is the better option then?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not necessarily.  Advertised comparison rates don’t include fee waivers, discounts or other benefits. In the example, Lender A regularly waives the application fee on request but Lender B does not.  This would make Lender A’s comparison rate 4.40%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-else-should-i-be-cautious-about-comparison-rates&quot;&gt;Why else should I be cautious about comparison rates?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The calculation does not take into account financial benefits gained from other features associated with the home loan such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest savings from a 100% offset account or loan trimmer account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Associated fee waivers on credit cards or bank accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Associated discounts on insurances and other services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-is-a-comparison-rate-good-for-then&quot;&gt;So what is a comparison rate good for then?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are very good when comparing introductory/fixed rate loans as the comparison is based on the full loan term not just the intro period.  Here’s an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lender A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lender B&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amount&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$350,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Term&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30yrs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30yrs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3yr Intro Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.99%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.99%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;After 3yr Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5.24%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.24%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Application Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$600&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$600&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$10 mth&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$10 mth&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Comparison Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.97%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.22%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The large difference in comparison rates quickly raises an alarm. It has revealed Lender A’s catch to their special offer.  That is a much higher rate after the intro term.  The comparison rate very quickly identified this issue without the borrower having to do too much analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;should-i-rely-on-comparison-rates-to-decide-what-loan-is-best&quot;&gt;Should I rely on comparison rates to decide what loan is best?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No.  They are a guide only.  Speak to a professional mortgage broker who will undertake a detailed comparison of all features, benefits &amp;amp; costs to ensure you have accurate information to be able to make good financial decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">A comparison rate is a tool to help consumers identify the true cost of a loan by reducing the costs of a loan—including interest &amp;amp; fees—into a single percentage rate to easily compare the true cost of home loans. We can use comparison rates to compare various loans from different lenders.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-comparison-rates.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Top 5 useless tips to save a deposit</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/top-5-not-so-great-tips-to-save-a-deposit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Top 5 useless tips to save a deposit" /><published>2017-06-02T17:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-02T17:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/top-5-not-so-great-tips-to-save-a-deposit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/top-5-not-so-great-tips-to-save-a-deposit/">&lt;p&gt;According to a recent newspaper article if you earn $150,000 p/a you can save $100,000 deposit in just 2 years. This is fantastic if you earn that sort of dough.  So it got me thinking, what other fairy tale ideas have others published all in the name of helping you save for a deposit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Here are my top 5 not-so-great tips on how to save a deposit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;switch-off-the-lights&quot;&gt;Switch off the Lights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows this one, the old switch off the lights when not in use but seriously, one light bulb running for one hour costs about 0.2cents! The big idea here is to save on utility bills like electricity &amp;amp; phones etc. With effort you can potentially save 20% but this might only equate to $800 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;switch-your-savings-to-a-high-interest-account&quot;&gt;Switch your savings to a high interest account&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason you’re saving is that you don’t have any!  If you did have $10,000 though at 2% and switched to 4%, you will make an extra $200 p/a interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sell-stuff-on-ebay&quot;&gt;Sell stuff on Ebay&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’ve sold my 90’s CD collection, a $10 K-Mart t-shirt I got for my birthday and a set of old car seat covers.  So I now have an extra $38.53 saved!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drink-instant-coffee-instead-of-buying-a-coffee-on-the-way-to-work&quot;&gt;Drink instant coffee instead of buying a coffee on the way to work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 days a week, 48 weeks a year, $5 a coffee, that’s $1,200 in 12mths.  But instant coffee!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-a-2nd-job&quot;&gt;Get a 2nd Job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work a few extra hours each week in a 2nd job and make an extra $200, less tax that’s $7,000 a year.  Fantastic idea if jobs were readily available.  Reality is you’re unlikely to find a job paying $200 a wk and flexible to fit in with current employer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tips might be useful if you’re saving for that new TV but the last time I checked, a house is a little more expensive than a flatscreen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">According to a recent newspaper article if you earn $150,000 p/a you can save $100,000 deposit in just 2 years. This is fantastic if you earn that sort of dough.  So it got me thinking, what other fairy tale ideas have others published all in the name of helping you save for a deposit.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /></entry></feed>