<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-05-08T13:27:28+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/</id><title type="html">LendFirst Home Loans</title><subtitle>LendFirst offers smart advice and real solutions for first home buyers and first-time investors, in Cairns, Queeensland, Australia.</subtitle><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><entry><title type="html">Introducing Lendfirst Home Loans, the low deposit experts</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/introducing-lendfirst-home-loans-the-low-deposit-experts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Lendfirst Home Loans, the low deposit experts" /><published>2017-05-08T11:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-08T11:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/introducing-lendfirst-home-loans-the-low-deposit-experts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/introducing-lendfirst-home-loans-the-low-deposit-experts/">&lt;p&gt;Lendfirst Home Loans (previously Australian Property Finance, Cairns) purpose is to assist undervalued low deposit and first home buyers find real solutions to buy their homes. First home buyers and low deposit buyers are regularly mislead by media, friends, family, banks and other advisers who say home ownership is not possible without a large deposit. This is simply not the case and many miss out because they listen to incorrect advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a first home buyer or have a limited deposit, Lendfirst Home Loans specialises in finding real solutions just for you.  Because we are experts in low deposit loans, we often get you a ‘Yes’ when others have already given you a ‘No’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will publish regular thought provoking and interesting articles via our weekly blog and provide regular informative explanations of policies, processes and systems needed to buy a house and/or get a home loan. Follow us on Facebook, visit our website or simply email to participate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><summary type="html">Lendfirst Home Loans (previously Australian Property Finance, Cairns) purpose is to assist undervalued low deposit and first home buyers find real solutions to buy their homes. First home buyers and low deposit buyers are regularly mislead by media, friends, family, banks and other advisers who say home ownership is not possible without a large deposit. This is simply not the case and many miss out because they listen to incorrect advice.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-introducing-lendfirst-home-loans,-the-low-deposit-experts.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">An unsuccessful debt reduction strategy</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/unsuccessful-debt-reduction-strategy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An unsuccessful debt reduction strategy" /><published>2016-09-04T23:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2016-09-04T23:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/unsuccessful-debt-reduction-strategy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/unsuccessful-debt-reduction-strategy/">&lt;p&gt;A client of mine, who we shall call Bob, earned an obscenely high amount of income, he drove a brand new BMW, always wore nice Italian suits and travelled overseas at least twice a year.  Ignoring stereotypes, Bob was actually a very down to earth, genuine nice guy but terrible with money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, he was advised to change his home loan to a revolving line of credit and open a credit card.  He was to put his salary into the line of credit and spend on the credit card.  At the end of the month he would transfer the credit card balance in full from the line of credit thus avoiding interest on the credit card and saving $100’s in interest on the home loan during the month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds great in theory however the one big flaw was the credit card limit the adviser gave Bob.  The limit on Bob’s credit card equalled his net monthly income so Bob being the spendthrift he was, blew his credit card limit every month and surprise surprise Bob’s home loan balance never reduced a cent in over 5yrs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve Bob’s problem, we first changed his home loan to a term loan with principal and interest repayments.  Not only did this give Bob a firm structure and plan to reduce his loan balance he also saved a bit of interest in the process as revolving line of credit facilities are more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we found a loan that had a full 100% offset included.  When used properly, this feature has the same benefit as a line of credit but forces the loan to reduce to zero after 30yrs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we reviewed Bob’s household budget and reduced his credit card limit to equal his monthly expenses not his monthly income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Utilising the same strategy as the previous adviser but with a different product and credit card limit in place Bob can now actually start paying his loan off sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to report that Bob has paid his loan off in under 5yrs but that would be a lie.  Bob couldn’t help himself and continues to spend like crazy but at least now his loan is reducing every month and each month he is building more and more equity in his home in the hope that one day, he will spend his money on something more useful, like an investment property perhaps!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><category term="problem solved" /><category term="debt" /><summary type="html">A client of mine, who we shall call Bob, earned an obscenely high amount of income, he drove a brand new BMW, always wore nice Italian suits and travelled overseas at least twice a year. Ignoring stereotypes, Bob was actually a very down to earth, genuine nice guy but terrible with money.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-an-unsuccessful-debt-reduction-strategy.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">5 reasons why pre-approvals are bad</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/5-reasons-why-pre-approvals-are-bad-for-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 reasons why pre-approvals are bad" /><published>2016-08-29T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2016-08-29T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/5-reasons-why-pre-approvals-are-bad-for-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/5-reasons-why-pre-approvals-are-bad-for-you/">&lt;p&gt;A pre-approval of finance before shopping for a house is common for many buyers and recommended by many lending experts but applying for a pre-approval could ruin your chances when it comes to making a formal application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top 5 reasons why a pre-approval is bad for you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-they-expire-after-90days&quot;&gt;1. They expire after 90days&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 90days you start from scratch again. A new application form and fresh information on everything you already provided is needed.  Even after 30 days, most lenders still require fresh payslips, bank statements etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-it-is-not-a-full-assessment&quot;&gt;2. It is not a full assessment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre-approvals have so many conditions in the fine print, they are practically a worthless piece of paper.  With most lenders, payslips are not checked, bank statements are not verified and mortgage insurers are never asked for approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-no-protection-against-policy-changes&quot;&gt;3. No protection against policy changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a lender changes policies during the 90days, the new policy will be enforced.  This happened in 2015 when thousands of investors were caught out by banks increasing minimum deposits for investors.  Many lost $1,000’s in deposits and fees because they relied upon a pre-approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-can-ruin-credit-historys&quot;&gt;4. Can ruin credit history’s&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time a lender does a pre-approval, an enquiry is made on your credit file. If you have multiple pre-approvals even with the same lender this will negatively impact on your credit.  This could result in a formal application being declined because the credit file is too ‘busy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-its-a-sneaky-sales-trick&quot;&gt;5. It’s a sneaky sales trick&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industry encourages pre-approvals because it stops buyers shopping around. Buyers can get locked into a bad deal because they can’t go to another lender as their credit file is now too busy and can only go with the lender who issued the original pre-approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some circumstances, a pre-approval can be extremely beneficial and is the best course of action for some applicants however for the most part, speaking with a highly trained and experienced mortgage broker can often give the buyer just as much confidence to make an offer without impacting on credit files or missing out on a really good deal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><category term="borrowing" /><summary type="html">A pre-approval of finance before shopping for a house is common for many buyers and recommended by many lending experts but applying for a pre-approval could ruin your chances when it comes to making a formal application.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-5-reasons-why-pre-approvals-are-bad.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixed or Variable—which is best for me?</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/fixed-or-variable-which-is-best-for-me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixed or Variable—which is best for me?" /><published>2016-08-22T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2016-08-22T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/fixed-or-variable-which-is-best-for-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/fixed-or-variable-which-is-best-for-me/">&lt;p&gt;In the great debate between fixed and variable rate loans there are those that are firmly planted in the always go variable and those that believe fixed rates are the only option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most borrowers have no idea which one to go with. Proponents of variable rates value flexibility and extra payments but those with fixed rate loans want their rate protected against rises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no right or wrong answer and the correct answer always depends on your situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you intend on selling your home soon, refinancing the loan, making extra repayments, subdividing or simply changing the name to a married/maiden name then you should consider going variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have no plans for any of the above and just want to ensure your repayments don’t change suddenly on you, then you should consider a fixed rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some fixed rate loans allow extra repayments and some even have an offset facility, so making extra/lump sum payments is still a possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, 80% of borrowers who choose a fixed rate loan are worse off at the end of their term had they of chosen variable.  Remember, the banks are very good at predicting interest rates and even better at making this work in their favour not yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So next time you choose between fixed or variable, make sure you choose for the right reasons, not because one is cheaper than the other.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><category term="interest rates" /><summary type="html">In the great debate between fixed and variable rate loans there are those that are firmly planted in the always go variable and those that believe fixed rates are the only option.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-fixed-or-variable-which-is-best-for-me.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Are you a DIY borrower?</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/are-you-a-diy-borrower/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are you a DIY borrower?" /><published>2016-08-15T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2016-08-15T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/are-you-a-diy-borrower</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/are-you-a-diy-borrower/">&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows one, the obsessive ‘DIY’er.  That one person who is so confident in their own ability that no-one, not even the experts can do a better job and do it cheaper.  That one person who has to show off how good they are at everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now don’t get me wrong there are some genius handymen out there that can fix anything, but the sad reality is, most of us don’t and usually make things worse and more expensive by trying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding a home loan is no different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going directly to a bank for a home loan, makes you a DIY borrower.  You only get information that is relevant for that bank, not what is relevant for you.
A client of mine wanted to upgrade to a bigger home but didn’t want to sell the old one first. They spoke to many banks directly and were told by all of them it was not possible and they had to sell first, rent then buy the new house, if it was still for sale.  This was avoided with a specialised bridging product from a smaller bank that allowed the client to buy first, move in and then sell the old saving the client considerable cost and inconvenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this client decided to DIY the solution, they would still be in a rental waiting for their dream home to come on the market again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brain surgery should not be a DIY activity and nor should getting a home loan. Do it right, get help from the right people and your ego will thank you for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><category term="borrowing" /><summary type="html">Everyone knows one, the obsessive ‘DIY’er. That one person who is so confident in their own ability that no-one, not even the experts can do a better job and do it cheaper. That one person who has to show off how good they are at everything.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-are-you-a-diy-borrower.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Who really controls your interest rates?</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/who-really-controls-your-interest-rates/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who really controls your interest rates?" /><published>2016-04-13T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2016-04-13T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/who-really-controls-your-interest-rates</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/who-really-controls-your-interest-rates/">&lt;p&gt;Does the Reserve Bank really have control over home loan interest rates? Most believe the Reserve Bank has ultimate control over interest rates. Every month, mortgage holders anxiously await the outcome of the RBA’s monthly board meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience is like servicing the family car and waiting for the bill.  The job is done and you know you have to pay for it no matter what but as the mechanic starts explaining he adjusted the ‘Pressure Feedback EGA Sensor’ and tightened the support bolts on the ‘A/C Clutch Field Coil’ you start thinking this is going to be expensive, but then he doesn’t charge you as it only took a minute to fix. You drive home feeling like you’ve just won the lotto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand who has ultimate control over your interest rates lets consider a shop owner who sells kitchen tables. If building a kitchen table requires one plank of timber at a cost of $200 the shop owner does not sell it for $200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same principle applies to money. If a bank buys money for 2%, it will not sell it for 2%.  Just like the shop owner, the bank must cover its costs and provide profit to its owners, otherwise it is just a charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shop owner can sell the kitchen table for whatever price he or she wants regardless of the raw cost of timber. If timber prices stay the same but cost of screws increase, the shop owner will increase the price of the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise if a rival furniture retailer sells the same table cheaper, the original shop owner reduces the price to compete. If the shop owner doesn’t manage this process well, they could soon be out of business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our banks operate exactly the same way and behave in the same manner as the shop owner, so next time your home loan rate changes ‘Out of Step’ with the reserve bank, just look at your kitchen table and think to yourself, maybe the price of screws have gone up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>patternworks_</name></author><category term="interest rates" /><category term="reserve bank" /><category term="mortgage" /><summary type="html">Does the Reserve Bank really have control over home loan interest rates? Most believe the Reserve Bank has ultimate control over interest rates. Every month, mortgage holders anxiously await the outcome of the RBA’s monthly board meeting.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-who-really-controls-your-interest-rates.jpg" /></entry></feed>