<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-17T13:55:32+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/feed.xml</id><title type="html">LendFirst Home Loans</title><subtitle>LendFirst offers smart advice and real solutions for first home buyers and first-time investors, in Cairns, Queeensland, Australia.</subtitle><author><name>callumflack</name></author><entry><title type="html">Life Insurance—it’s not a scam!</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/life-insurance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life Insurance—it’s not a scam!" /><published>2017-12-21T14:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-12-21T14:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/life-insurance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/life-insurance/">&lt;p&gt;This week I’d like to share with you one of the most difficult conversations I have had in over 20 years in the finance industry. I don’t share this to worry you, but to make you think hard when you’re taking out a loan as to what you would do if the worst was to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dave took out a home loan and at that time he did the right thing and reviewed his life assurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a fit young man who worked hard and had no health worries. He ate healthily and didn’t smoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 years into his loan, Dave was diagnosed with terminal cancer. He was the only income earner and would be leaving his wife alone with their 2 children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I hadn’t sorted out his home loan, Dave asked me to help him to access his insurance to pay it out. There was no record of any insurance cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the records did show that when Dave reviewed his life assurance, he decided that he would not take it out as he felt that the cost was just too high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was obviously devastating news. He knew that without him, his family would be unable to continue in the family home. In fact, they were likely to have nowhere to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a true story and the single hardest conversation I have ever had with a client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Lendfirst Home Loans we make no apologies for advising clients to seek independent advice from an insurance specialist with every home loan application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of a monthly premium is one thing, the cost of leaving a family in this situation is one that no one should ever have to pay.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="comment" /><summary type="html">This week I’d like to share with you one of the most difficult conversations I have had in over 20 years in the finance industry. I don’t share this to worry you, but to make you think hard when you’re taking out a loan as to what you would do if the worst was to happen.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-life-insurance.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-life-insurance.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Employment Type—Self Employed</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/employment-type-self-employed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Employment Type—Self Employed" /><published>2017-12-14T09:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-12-14T09:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/employment-type-self-employed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/employment-type-self-employed/">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to taking out a home loan, self-employed income and employment is a little
more complicated than for traditionally employed people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick is to be clear on what kind of employment you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re self-employed, you will have an Australian Business Number – usually called an
ABN. You’re also responsible for paying your own tax and superannuation, unlike being
employed, where your employer pays your tax and superannuation whether you’re full-time,
part-time or casual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, looking at how you’re employed is important…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At LendFirst we ask some simple questions to get to the answer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Does your employer give you a payslip” = You’re employed (or PAYG as it’s often called)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Does your employer give you a Tax Invoice?” = You’re self-employed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people change from being employed to being a contract employee. Even if you work
at the same company, doing the same work with the same people but your ‘status’ changes
from employed to contractor, lenders will look at this as though you resigned from your
job and started a new contract role. This can have an impact on whether they will lend to
you. And how you are paid is important too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being self-employed, your income can vary from week to week. Lenders usually want to see
self-employed applicants trade for at least 2 full years before considering their income
as stable enough to decide how much they can lend you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some lenders will consider self-employed applicants after 6 or 12mths. However the deposit
you need will be significantly higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-points&quot;&gt;Key Points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re self-employed, or think you may be, talk to LendFirst and we’ll help you
through the maze.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure you have records for your income. Your tax return is really important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">When it comes to taking out a home loan, self-employed income and employment is a little more complicated than for traditionally employed people.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Full Time? Part Time? Or Casual—What’s the difference?</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/full-time-part-time-casual-whats-the-difference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Full Time? Part Time? Or Casual—What’s the difference?" /><published>2017-12-07T14:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-12-07T14:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/full-time-part-time-casual-whats-the-difference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/full-time-part-time-casual-whats-the-difference/">&lt;p&gt;Any lender will look at what type of employment you have, not just what income you get,
when you apply for a loan. Your employment history gives them an indication of your
likelihood to continue to work, and of course, pay your loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a guide to the main types of employment and how lenders look at them when
assessing your loan application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;full-time&quot;&gt;Full Time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You work for the same employer ‘full time‘, that is, a minimum of 38 hours each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are away from work for holidays, or because you’re ill, your employer will still to
pay you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenders like full time employees because your income is consistent and there’s a higher
chance that you will stay in the same job once they have given you the loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-time&quot;&gt;Part Time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part time is pretty much the same as full time, with the only difference being that you
would work fewer than 38 hours each week. Lenders look favourably on part time employees
too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;casual&quot;&gt;Casual&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casual sounds like a more flexible type of employment and it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hours each week may vary and there’s no holiday pay or sick pay. Income is usually higher
as it is ‘loaded’ to cover for the lack of holiday and sick pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenders are often a bit more cautious with Casual employees as their income can vary from
week to week. If you have been with the same employer for more than 12 months, lenders are
a little more relaxed but will consider the income in a slightly different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;length-of-time&quot;&gt;Length of time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the type of employment, lenders look to see how long you have been in the same
job or industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have been in the same industry for 2 years, you usually only need to have been in
the same job for 1 complete pay period for part and full-time employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have switched industry, or have had time off between jobs then lenders usually
expect you to have been in your job for 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re casual lenders usually look for you to be in the same job continuously for 12
months&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-points&quot;&gt;Key Points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re not sure of your employment type, talk to us at LendFirst and we’ll help you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re casual and haven’t worked continuously for 12 months, then talk to us as we
may still be able to help&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re thinking about buying your first home, think hard before you change your job
or industry as it can affect your ability to get a loan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">Any lender will look at what type of employment you have, not just what income you get, when you apply for a loan. Your employment history gives them an indication of your likelihood to continue to work, and of course, pay your loan.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The best way to benefit from the First Home Owners Grant</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/the-best-way-to-benefit-from-the-first-home-owners-grant/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The best way to benefit from the First Home Owners Grant" /><published>2017-11-16T14:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-11-16T14:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/the-best-way-to-benefit-from-the-first-home-owners-grant</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/the-best-way-to-benefit-from-the-first-home-owners-grant/">&lt;p&gt;First home buyers will be aware of the Queensland Government’s First Home Owner’s Grant. Builders are advertising it, and lots of lenders are promoting it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It certainly sounds like a great way to build a brand-new home and, available until 31st December, it is a generous offer from the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest hurdle for First Home Buyers is definitely saving the deposit. A 5% deposit on the average home of $400,000 in Cairns is $20,000. So a $20,000 grant from the government sounds just right. Unfortunately, it’s not that simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building&quot;&gt;Building&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’re building your new home, lenders do not take the $20,000 grant into account when determining what deposit you will need. You still need to have the 5% deposit from your own savings to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because of the timing of the grant payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant becomes available when the slab is completed. So, you have to pay the 5% deposit on the purchase of the land and also the 5% builder’s deposit before the grant is paid. You can then spend the grant money on paying down your loan (depending on the type), furniture, landscaping or a new car for example once it’s paid to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buying&quot;&gt;Buying&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re buying a brand-new house or unit that has already been built &amp;amp; is ready to move in then it works a bit differently!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you’re not waiting for the ‘slab stage’ as it’s already been completed, many lenders will allow you to use the grant as your deposit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because of the timing – the grant is available on the day you settle which means it is possible to buy a brand-new home for $400k using the $20k grant as your deposit. The settlement on the land and the completed property happens all at once and the ‘slab stage’ was at the very start of the build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you’re keen to choose your own block and design your own home, you’ll need to make sure you have that deposit saved. But, if you’re willing to limit yourself to the very small amount of properties available from builders that fully have constructed new homes, then you may be able to use the grant as a deposit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the majority of people, the grant doesn’t help you get into your new home sooner, but gives you a great helping hand once you have moved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-points&quot;&gt;Key Points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t rely on the grant for your deposit – get saving!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are not many new homes that builders have funded to full construction, so don’t expect to find the home you want in these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk to LendFirst Home Loans and we can make sure you get the best advice on the full new home buying or building process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move quickly – the grant is due to end on 31st December 2017 and you don’t want to miss out!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="comment" /><summary type="html">First home buyers will be aware of the Queensland Government’s First Home Owner’s Grant. Builders are advertising it, and lots of lenders are promoting it too.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-first-home-owners-grant.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-first-home-owners-grant.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Home Loan Pre-Approvals</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/home-loan-pre-approvals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Home Loan Pre-Approvals" /><published>2017-11-09T22:34:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-11-09T22:34:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/home-loan-pre-approvals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/home-loan-pre-approvals/">&lt;p&gt;Pre-Approvals, are they as helpful as they sound? Firstly, let’s just see what Pre-Approval actually means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenders will tell you to apply to them for a pre-approval which sounds like you’re sorted before you go house-hunting. But it literally means ‘at a stage before approval’, so, pre-approval creates no obligation whatsoever on the lender and no real rights to you as the potential borrower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, one of the most common phrases I hear from first home buyers is ‘The bank pre-approved me for a loan but when I found a house they said no!’ which can be very disappointing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if they are done correctly, they are invaluable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some lenders get you to fully apply for a loan whereas others simply provide a preliminary review by an experienced adviser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference when you make a full application for a loan is that the lender will make an enquiry on your credit file, which is recorded. This can then make a difference if you start to shop around (see my blog credit file). A preliminary review does not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you’re sure that you’ve got the right lender, and the right home for you – don’t make a full application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why do lenders and advisers recommend a full application?  Usually so that you’re locked into them and it’s easier for you to stay with them rather than shop around – even if they don’t have the best deal for you. Or, the adviser may not have the experience or the confidence to give you an answer just from a preliminary review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lendfirst Home Loans will never make a full application until we know it’s the best thing for you, and certainly not for a pre-approval.  We have lots of experience and the confidence to give you a reliable guide before you start house-hunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t make a full loan application when you only need a pre-approval&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be cautious if someone insists that you make a pre-approval application with one specific lender&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk to Lendfirst for honest and reliable information and support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">Pre-Approvals, are they as helpful as they sound? Firstly, let’s just see what Pre-Approval actually means.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Buying Apartments &amp;amp; Units</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/buying-apartments-and-units/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buying Apartments &amp;amp; Units" /><published>2017-10-26T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-10-26T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/buying-apartments-and-units</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/buying-apartments-and-units/">&lt;p&gt;Apartment living, especially in cities, is a modern, and often more affordable way of getting onto the property ladder. But I can’t stress enough how important it is to do a bit of home work first – lenders can be particular about what unit or apartment you’re trying to buy. As experts in the Cairns market and first home owner lending, LendFirst can help you make the right selection up front. Here’s a few examples of what lenders will and won’t do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;size-matters&quot;&gt;Size Matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The living area, not including any car spaces or balconies, must usually be at least 50m2. Some lenders will look at 40m2 at a push. The property also needs to have at least one separate fully enclosed bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;postcodes-and-deposits&quot;&gt;Postcodes and deposits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenders require bigger deposits in some areas, particularly capital cities. In the Cairns region, the postcodes affected are 4870 &amp;amp; 4879. Here you may need 10%-20% deposit if there are more than 10 units in the complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;complex-complexes&quot;&gt;Complex Complexes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenders will look at different types of complexes differently. Some of the different types are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Traditional&lt;/strong&gt; - all units are occupied permanently by their owners or rented to long term tenants. These complexes are the most common and are widely accepted by lenders.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resorts&lt;/strong&gt; - resort or holiday apartment complex units are harder to get a loan for. They are either not accepted at all, or you need 20%-30% deposit for the lender to even consider your loan – that can be as much as $45,000 on a property of $150,000. If there’s an onsite manager or office managing the complex, it’s likely to be a resort.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A mix!&lt;/strong&gt; - some complexes are not quite resorts/holiday apartments but are also not quite traditional either. They allow a mix of both holiday letting and permanent owner occupiers and they may or may not have an onsite manager. These complexes are often acceptable if you can show that you will live in your property on a permanent basis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;too-many-loans-with-one-lender&quot;&gt;Too many loans with one lender&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes lots of buyers in the same complex will get their loans from the same lender. The lenders don’t always like this, so will put a ceiling on how many loans they will do in each complex. This means that they may decline some new loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no way to check this until you make your application – but it doesn’t happen often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using LendFirst for your loan means that if this does happen, we simply talk to one of our other lenders and sort it out without hassle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-go-there&quot;&gt;Don’t go there!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some property types that lenders won’t consider at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Studio Apartments&lt;/strong&gt; - no separate bedroom. The bedroom is in the same open space as the kitchen, lounge or dining area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student Accommodation&lt;/strong&gt; - usually shared bathrooms and kitchens with individual rooms let&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dual Key&lt;/strong&gt; - one unit is divided into 2 using a lockable internal door. These are mostly found in resort/holiday apartments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hotel/Motel&lt;/strong&gt; - these are considered ‘serviced apartments’ and are usually unacceptable to lenders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Share&lt;/strong&gt; - where ownership is shared with other people and access is limited to a specific number of days or weeks each year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company title&lt;/strong&gt; - an older style where the block of units is owned by a company and ownership of ‘shares’ shows ownership of a particular unit. The main problem with these properties is that the consent of the other owners may be needed to sell, lease or mortgage your unit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As first home owner specialists, LendFirst are experts in helping with unit or apartment purchase. We’ll help you through the maze, make it simple and help you to make wise decisions when purchasing this kind of property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-points&quot;&gt;Key Points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check the size of the property before you go and fall in love with it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask questions about the other property owners and occupiers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk to LendFirst to make sure you’re looking at the right property types&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="comment" /><summary type="html">Apartment living, especially in cities, is a modern, and often more affordable way of getting onto the property ladder. But I can’t stress enough how important it is to do a bit of home work first – lenders can be particular about what unit or apartment you’re trying to buy. As experts in the Cairns market and first home owner lending, LendFirst can help you make the right selection up front. Here’s a few examples of what lenders will and won’t do.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-buying-apartments-and-units.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-buying-apartments-and-units.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Open Home Etiquette—the do’s and don’ts</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/open-home-etiquette/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open Home Etiquette—the do’s and don’ts" /><published>2017-10-19T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/open-home-etiquette</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/open-home-etiquette/">&lt;p&gt;We would all like to think we have good manners, but when you haven’t done something before it can be confusing to know just what’s expected of you. Take looking at someone else’s home. We know it’s probably not OK to grab a beer from the fridge, but what else should we do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give yourself plenty of time.&lt;/strong&gt; Arriving at 1:59 when the open home finishes at 2 is not a great start.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make sure you park politely.&lt;/strong&gt; Parking in the driveway is a no-no until you own the home.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test the drawers and cupboards—once not ten times.&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t go through every drawer and cupboard either.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take your shoes off.&lt;/strong&gt; Wear thongs that you can leave on the doorstep. People have probably had the floors cleaned for this inspection.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bring a tape measure.&lt;/strong&gt; You’ll need one to check that your furniture, fridge and TV fit in the space you’re seeing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talk to the agent.&lt;/strong&gt; They are likely to remember the courteous people and can help you with this purchase—or notify you of others that come on the market.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally—go to the loo before you inspect.&lt;/strong&gt; Do not, I repeat, do not, use the toilet. I can’t stress this enough!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy looking at your potential new home, and if you need any more hints and tips or what to look for when you’re inspecting just get in touch!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">We would all like to think we have good manners, but when you haven’t done something before it can be confusing to know just what’s expected of you. Take looking at someone else’s home. We know it’s probably not OK to grab a beer from the fridge, but what else should we do?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Family Guarantee</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/family-guarantee/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Family Guarantee" /><published>2017-10-12T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-10-12T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/family-guarantee</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/family-guarantee/">&lt;p&gt;You could be mistaken for thinking that a family guarantee is some sort of Mafia loyalty pledge – but it’s actually a really smart way for first home buyers to buy their first home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows how difficult it can be for first home owners to save a deposit – and then there’s Lender’s Mortgage Insurance (find out more in my blog) to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another way! A Family Guarantee is basically parents, or grandparents, guaranteeing that they will cover the bank’s losses should the buyer default on their loan. You may also hear ‘Parental Guarantee’, ‘Family Pledge’ or ‘Limited Guarantee’ all of which mean the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-they-guaranteeing&quot;&gt;What are they guaranteeing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person giving the guarantee is basically saying that, if the person buying their home defaults, then they promise to cover the debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You buy a house for $400,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You borrow from the bank $400,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Family guarantee $80,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guarantee, usually ‘secured’ against the family member’s home, is 20% of the cost of the house, avoiding the need to pay Lender’s Mortgage Insurance, or save a deposit. So, the property ladder is no longer out of reach. The family member will be known as ‘the guarantor’. This a ‘limited’ guarantee – limited to $80,000 in the example above.  It’s important for the first-time buyer to make the loan repayments, as their parents would probably be pretty unhappy if they didn’t! For this reason, banks will still do a thorough check to make sure the borrower can afford the monthly payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-at-risk-for-the-guarantor&quot;&gt;What’s at risk for the guarantor?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the borrower defaults, and the property has to be sold, then in our example, the bank can claim up to the $80,000 guarantee if they make a loss. The amounts would change for different purchase prices. Your broker will make sure you know what’s what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the bank doesn’t make a loss, and the property sells for a lot more, then the guarantee will not be used.  The worst-case scenario is the guarantors may have to sell their house they used as security for the guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guarantors also need to think about whether they will need to borrow any money themselves, as the banks will take this guarantee into account when assessing how much they can borrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guarantors should ALWAYS seek independent legal advice before entering into an arrangement like this. There may be a cost for this but it’s worth it in the long run. LendFirst will also talk to them in depth about their obligations and what it all means – we see it as a key part of looking after our customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-long-is-the-guarantee&quot;&gt;How long is the guarantee?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guarantee is for the life of the loan, up to 30yrs. The bank can reassess the loan and release the guarantor if they are happy that they have enough security, for example, if property prices have gone up sufficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LendFirst Home Loans will always help you to structure your loan to ensure that the guarantor can be removed sooner rather than later.
Who can be a guarantor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most banks only allow parents to be guarantor but some allow siblings.  More distant relations cannot usually be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guarantors who are working, or can provide investment property to support the loan are usually accepted. Retired guarantors with little savings who would use their home as security for the pledge are usually not acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-i-still-get-the-20k-first-home-owners-grant&quot;&gt;Can I still get the $20k First Home Owners Grant?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes – but disclose on your application that you are receiving financial help from the guarantors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-points&quot;&gt;Key points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk to LendFirst, and get your guarantor to talk to us too&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure you’re comfortable with the monthly repayments for the loan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure the guarantor gets legal advice and understands exactly what they’re getting into&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">You could be mistaken for thinking that a family guarantee is some sort of Mafia loyalty pledge – but it’s actually a really smart way for first home buyers to buy their first home.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Renting to Buying — an easy step?</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/renting-to-buy-an-easy-step/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renting to Buying — an easy step?" /><published>2017-10-04T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-10-04T07:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/renting-to-buy-an-easy-step</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/renting-to-buy-an-easy-step/">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve made the decision to change from renting to buying your own home then congratulations! There are lots of benefits to owning your own home. Before you search for your perfect home it’s best to make sure you work out what you can afford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re renting in Cairns, it’s likely that you’re paying on average around $350 per week. When you’re an owner your expenses change, so don’t just use your rental payment to work out how much you can borrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-should-check-first&quot;&gt;What you should check first&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure your credit rating is in order —  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/am-i-credit-worthy-what-you-need-to-know/&quot;&gt;my earlier blog post&lt;/a&gt; gives you some good hints and tips on how to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sort your budget before house-hunting — not the other way around. There are extra costs when you are a home owner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rates — Your expenses can change by around $50 per week as a property owner rather than tenant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Insurance — you’ll now need to insure the building, not just your contents, adding around $30 per week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also need to make sure you can make your payments if interest rates rise. A rate increase of 2% adds $80 per week to loan repayments on a $280,000 loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your broker will work through your finances with you and help you to sort out exactly what you can afford to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also ask yourself a simple question: “If my rent increased by $150 per week, could I still afford to live where I am now?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only have to tweak your lifestyle a little — perhaps to stop eating out quite as much - then you’re probably on the right track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d have to move to a cheaper rental to make the payments, then you may need to consider buying a home in a lower price range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-points&quot;&gt;Key points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about costs that you will have as an owner that you don’t have as a tenant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider what you can afford now — and if interest rates go up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk to your broker who will give you all the information and help you need to make the step to home ownership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="comment" /><summary type="html">If you’ve made the decision to change from renting to buying your own home then congratulations! There are lots of benefits to owning your own home. Before you search for your perfect home it’s best to make sure you work out what you can afford.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-does-renting-prove.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/uploads/post-does-renting-prove.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Settlement Date!</title><link href="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/settlement-date/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Settlement Date!" /><published>2017-09-27T20:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-09-27T20:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/settlement-date</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lendfirst.com.au/blog/settlement-date/">&lt;p&gt;There’s lots of jargon when you’re buying a home, and do you know what? You’ll only ever need to know what they mean when you’re going through the process. It can seem like the banks and solicitors have made up these words (and maybe they have) so let me make sense of one for you today – settlement date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-it&quot;&gt;What is it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is simply the official day that ownership of the home transfers to the person that’s buying it. You may also hear this described as the ‘title’ of the property being exchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day when money and property title are exchanged between buyer and seller and ownership of the property officially transfers to the buyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;just-before-settlement&quot;&gt;Just before settlement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your broker and solicitor will keep in touch with you in the run up to your settlement date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will let you know if there’s anything you need to do. Usually this is making sure that your solicitor has your deposit on settlement day so that it can actually happen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also go and have another look at the property before you settle. This is called a ‘pre-settlement inspection’. If you included anything in the contract that needed doing (known as a ‘special condition’), like repairing a broken fence, it’s recommended that you take a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your solicitor will help you if you have any questions about what you should include as a special condition on the contract. You can find out more about contracts on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.qld.gov.au/law/housing-and-neighbours/buying-and-selling-a-property/buying-a-home/making-an-offer-on-a-home/contract-of-sale&quot;&gt;this helpful government website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-happens&quot;&gt;So what happens?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your solicitor, your bank, the seller’s solicitor and the sellers bank all get together, usually at seller’s bank or the seller’s solicitor office. You don’t need to be there – but have your phone handy in case they need to get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, after those weeks of planning and organising, the actual change of ownership only takes about 5 minutes! It’s amazing. More than 1.5 trillion loans are settled each year in Australia, so the process has been practised a few times and is really well organised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-is-settlement-day&quot;&gt;When is Settlement Day?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will have agreed settlement day as part of your contract, and each one is different. You can only change this if both you and the seller agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you miss the agreed settlement date you may be ‘in breach of contract’, meaning that you have not done what you said you would do. This can mean that the contract can be terminated completely by the seller and you may have to pay a substantial penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it’s best for buyers and sellers do everything they possibly can to make sure they hit that agreed settlement date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;after-settlement-day&quot;&gt;After Settlement Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve taken out a home loan your broker will have given you all of the information about how it will work. Settlement day, as well as the day that the property becomes yours, is also the day that your home loan officially starts. Your lender will confirm your payment to you, and interest will start to be charged by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, get in touch with your broker. There’s been a lot to take in and they won’t mind you asking as many questions as you need to.  After all, your home is probably the biggest purchase you’re going to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-points&quot;&gt;Key points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure you seek legal advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask your broker as many questions as you like – there’s no such thing as stupid question&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep to the settlement date in the contract&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enjoy your new home!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>callumflack</name></author><category term="tips" /><summary type="html">There’s lots of jargon when you’re buying a home, and do you know what? You’ll only ever need to know what they mean when you’re going through the process. It can seem like the banks and solicitors have made up these words (and maybe they have) so let me make sense of one for you today – settlement date.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lendfirst.com.au/true" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>